let's now have a look at multi-threading
models there are two ways in which you can
get your application or your process to run in a
multi-threaded fashion you can go for user threads
so you can manage threads completely at the user
level there are libraries for that of course
you don't have to do everything yourself but if
you think about it for a moment what I'm trying to
say here is that in principle you could write
your code so that instead of just running the
next instruction of a certain function you
have some meta code meta instructions that
periodically check let's say which function to run
and then select one appropriately okay so you can
manage threads at the user level you don't have
to do everything yourself you can do it at the
at the user level to make a very
very simple example if you have a process
and this process should run the
spell checker but also
run something else for example check if there
are software updates from the internet
you could write a function that checks for updates
a function that runs the spell
checker okay but these functions could be written
in a way so that periodically they get back to
another function and this function is the one that
decides which one of the two to run so you can
emulate threads at the user level
by writing code that makes sure that
let's say half of the time you do something
and also the time you're doing something else
you can do all these things at the user level
on the other end you can do this at the
kernel level letting the threads
operate inside the kernel and with this is
what you usually do with modern operating system
and modern hardware so there are different
threading models there is the many to one one to one
and many too many and I understand at this point
some of them might sound a bit strange but
hopefully during this lecture and during
also the following one on scheduling it will get a
bit clearer why you want to do something like this
if you go to many-to-one threads what you
do is that you define several threads at the user
level but you define a single thread at the kernel
level so from the operating system perspective and
from the hardware perspective you are running a
process that is running a single thread
but at the user level using a supporting
library you can periodically change let's say
which function you run which portion of code
so that you can achieve for example balance
between the different functions what is tricky here
is that since the operating system
sees everything as a
single thread as soon as one of your user threads
request something through a system call the
entire process will go into waiting mode
so in this case it's useless to have
many user level threads if one of them
tries to interact with the operating system through
a system call or generates an interrupt because
all of them will be put into waiting because for
the operating system everything is a single thread
the multithreaded execution is being
managed at the user level the other alternative
is to go one to one for each user level thread you
define a kernel thread in this case if your
thread that checks for updates from the internet
requires interaction with the operating system
through a system call because it needs to check
something that needs to go through the network
card that thread can be put into waiting but
the other thread that runs the spell checker and
it doesn't really need input/output with the
hardware because it just needs to check what
is in memory and whether what your writing is
correct or not can keep running of course this
takes more resources for the operating system
because you have to create separate threads and
the operating system needs to be aware that these
are different threads that belong to the same process
and as you might imagine it's also
less efficient because here you can
have context switches between the different
threads at the operating system level
the more general one or let's say the
one in in between is the many-to-many
model so you could say well there are a certain
number of user-level threads and these are mapped
to a certain set of kernel level threads okay
and the mapping can be changing dynamically
depending on basically the execution what your
code is trying to do and so on